All right so we're back in build two thousand fifteen lightbulb
...back in may have thousand good...rector peter tour of the windows...you
learned today about the wind universal windows platform so we want to
talk today of a couple of the program managers who were sort of leading the designer for their
for that api set to talk about the api set and what actually means so the first question I would
ask essentially how did you arrive at a universal windows api
...how did...work...off that on
...sowhat we did was we had windows...a one they had a
survey...available to them and we...windows phone a major one...belgium
...available...to do was basically bring the best of all these things together
and expand on it so that we could add more capabilities to
...so we ...will tell us a little bit about how what percentage of
...functionality taught inside universe windows platform we started with these three divest platforms
brought them together into one and then we listen to a lot of customer feedback about things
or missing...so there's many examples one out...for example,
threads in windows eight one windows finite
...those were not to thread pool but we didn't use the traditional
...thirty-two api like create...etc with a lot of customer feedback about that which
...that so when you have this windows platform...windows ten now includes a lot more
...like threading on more...who want to but based
...customer feedback and relapse we had people building
a windows virtually expanded that
...just what was interesting platforms lowest common denominator like this tiny little lump
of functionality was take what's in
these in these three different platforms bring the boca together and
expanded all-out...feedback awesome and one thing that I wanted to
highlight is the default policy going forward is new api
...part of the universal plan so we're trying not to fragment the api and say this is
an xbox api sort only ends up on the xbox device or
...phone api the default policy is to put the api everyone?
Now there's some subtleties there like, for example.
Making up a scanner...probably will never have a scanner on...
xbox just doesn't make a lot of sense the api is there.
Because so if I...app that wants to use of scanner...the natural api and
say give me...the scanners on this device and the api
...works on xbox they'll say well they're
...here just like on desktop if you didn't have any plugged in so
developers are not going to have to the...I can help whichhave to
write different code for different devices which they had to do traditionally
...universal windows platform is really to the extent we can humanly make
...universal?
And, I think just building...said in the past again with windows,
windows phone...xbox you could have a similar source code base but
...would if that's if that photon...that in the new world even where there
are cases where maybe there is an api for legacy reasons only actually
exists on xbox needed...anymore you can actually seems
...so runtime this...be talking about on friday you...friday
friday's at runtime you can detect ocean I...scanner api should I
called up the windows...back but maybe I should I call this api know if
...a single qubits truly a single code base so before we get to question of
...thank you man...niners been asking questions for years.
How does universal apps work on io...surely not required
dubious so how does universal apps on t work?
Surely they don't require you to...from the store out where
...you asking...so...the first question so
...to platform is part of the universe windows platform so you can
rights universal windows epsilon io...hire to epsy right
...windows absolute work on phone xbox...et cetera et cetera
the distribution of apps on I...can be different I'm not an expert on that.
So, I correct answer that the
school part of it but yes they are universe windows apps they have the same api
...every other universe windows up has is just a windows...
the only thing I would add is there are differences between devices for you so you want
to think about that when we talk about universe lap you can write one code base compile it
deployed all these devices same api is for all practical purposes
...available everywhere but if you projecting to a
ten foot screen or
...hollow lens on a fitness band or some future device
and you probably want to have different uri but you can either there's something called adaptive
...of you online those animal team has a presentation today
and multiple about...and,
that's not actually might area of expertise mine is more the actual api itself so
if I were writing...an app for io t have the choice it'll run on everywhere
I want the same ui everywhere probably not so you'd customize so
...for io t you probably have a customize ui for a
desktop for laptop or tablet but that can all be in one...can be...minor.
...wants to know now that dot net...ported to linux
...macro...which is an excellent taking on rightdo you see universal apps running on
android ios and universal out?
So, taking...the rt if you will and moving on different platforms.
We haven't discussed...anything like that
founder question get past security great question so the
...also wants to know does this universal philosophy apply...windows servers.
It does.
There's a deploying apps to the server means most servers may not want to
...apps from the store so ignoring the deployment aspect because you can always
side loader and stall them yourself the...rt and
...thirty-two subset of the api is role their present on the
servers skew we actually have a model and this is more of an internal
detailed...may be interesting of one core
platform it's the universal operating system if you will is made up
the term marketing has not approved...
...core platform is common to all
the devices including server including client including...
Including phone so the majority.
To the extent that we make an api universal which is like I said the default we
...do we put it on one core and becomes available on all platform.
But, of course servers habit sorbet different workload
...so you're not going to necessarily need to have we...jeffries
...talking about...nano...being a really small footprint
...right obviously don't have any of the...staff or any of that...right.
...let's see locust wants to...windows ten universal
out provide pdf api support phone devices I believe they do we had to
...windows I don't want I believe...been...universal ...off the top of my
head without looking and I'm very I'm very...show I can't tell you...I question
very show that...became universal now great are responsible
...still be differences such as those the bluetooth api that's actually a great question...a number problems
...you myself if not can be expected do sdk for microsoft
pantsuits possum work ok so there's
an interesting thing here where in windows I don't want to windows phone
...one we each had a large to if commonality amongst
...service area but we had vema with...we had a lot of the devices the same we
had the at models...guys with the...but...underlying implementation...quite different right so
...the kernel with the...and api...the top...time the stuff in the middle is not
necessarily the same...these differences in whether...which is stack
...in audio whether it's in something else where look the same...differently
as...saying with this move to one...one...we can this thing in the
...not the same kind of...so yes you should see all those differences between phone and windows
...xbox...away great and fundamentally
...type things universal windows platform was
envision to
...sarin have to go I can't do this bluetooth operations on the phone but I can
on a tablet we wanted...unify those to make...a common behavior
...common programming surface...the extent humanly possible I think we
get a really good job of getting there and we'll tell me people are going to start using you'll get
feedback any tools that
will help converting kurt windows phone windows store apps into universal?
Sadly the answer is no there I
...community and,
potentially even microsoft's as well to do that but today if you have a windows
...one app the migration is pretty much a manual process with the current visual
studio tools that we just-released it's actually quite straightforward having
done it probably twenty five times the last two weeks I but,
maybe it's only straightforward
...for the twenty-fifth time but really what...will can write man pages or
...on that and it's really pretty the tricky one would be if you had
a silverlight...overload lehrer another chemical, you know, so,
...silverlight...app universal
...more challenging because of course...not towards downloads windows animal
...set of api of our different sub-set but from a well-used to be called universal
at last year whether to windows or phone version should be much closer to and
...upright...project yet we just dragging all of your files and
...doesn't mean that model you had a shared core...you have to have
...for...can actually do that then add a universal head...references the other stuff
and drag stuff down of time...noted do them doing that the
math use the new windows ten universe lapped you have one
head it's just universal out...much simpler and
one sample yes right which is what you're alluding to...like five or six versions of our
...the at so congratulations on...them yone
everything that's the exes to be for active member the...yes right...just go one everything.
Well, universal out
...csharp be able to take advantage of dot net...compile a native code.
So, I can get a performance...yes.
And, it's not just take advantage of but they're all going to be gone basically when you build a managed
...manage universal...compile the...the native code great for all platforms
and the I'll and then you get links on install time on the phone.
Right that's and implementation detail may happen
...store great get length as well but the
net result is you compile csharp you'll get native as
on arm code one-thirty to attributes are whatever the...and that's all taken care of
Of how windows...able to publish apps on the xbox store they have to get through
ideas xbox or something similar.
It's not...windows...
A lot actually that's a great question we'll ask the people who
know where I can answer that I don't know the answer so there's a universal platform mean that there's a
security risk there's a bug within the windows universal base...surprises taken
so long for this question to be...nice job thomas I was an interesting question right the
vector now much larger you have the same code...on this issue.
While I'm not going through it because I'm that way I mean it's the same on any
kernel if there's a bug in a colonel
...being used on multiple devices then you have that
risk everywhere but it's also much simpler...because you forensic once and
you fix that everywhere too so I don't think that's unique to the universal flash
...all definitely not...it's a worthy question.
Is a direct x twelve api...universal windows phone...form and windows phone
ten direct...and I don't know about that
...certainly is there but, I don't know...of the hardware on phone can do it
all features...not the graphics...understood so what is the small-screen size requirement for you
ab ui uw p...development count io
...pretty darn small...
...in ranges there's...
I think we have guidelines for smaller than this...here's how
your ui should look and feel and probably interact what's the interaction model with
touch bigger screens like tv's there's a different
...by universal technically you don't need any screen role to be
universe.
But, there are that we published the minimum screen sizes release
...phone devices...windows ...resize windows you can actually
said preferences now so you can say I prefer to be the size and if we can give that gee
we'll give you that size...sizing is actually a lot richer in windows ten but, yeah,
there's really no minimum because it could be no system...
So, abstract said silverlight so talking about silverlight for windows phone...the universal
...api available in windows
...that one I'm not sure about.
Next question hra exist on the and without looking again
...about twelve thousand api is just in the winter to universals surface or
...which is something I really want to talk about some point was how you kind of rapture
heads around making decisions that this api makes
...api doesn't make it obviously a partners
...api...app or skylight team, for example, for,
yeah,...kind of make sense...move that across but there's so many...that, you know,
the one api the code name fumes...no,...story...you
know-how you kind of came across as a group of api designers to develop a really,
really large api stuff...sure that you nailed we
have course we have the business constraint we have so much time.
So, the pot more apps that you want to use and api or want to use the functionality
...that like any developer team...and if they were there on
the phone and on windows on desktop before
we said are they identical that's no-brainer than months
...that and universal the harder ones were they were different and I could go in
...lots of details on some of the ways they were different and unpleasant
...discover manner and we had the unify those which was a harder,
harder problem but it was really driven about how many developers would
use of...the features that
a niche feature that three of my friends would use but nobody else in the world
would then I would get out voted just...my friends they didn't get the rank and
...terms of...windows platform...the...a dot net started things we...a lot with
...dot net team who working on...mentioned...the...working on different platforms
...there's a bunch of core dot net api that we want to have a...on windows universal again in windows,
windows I and I don't want that dot net...relatively small because one of kind of
...was minimized duplication I...be...bone yes what kind of
...back a bit...to three ways a great if it helps people limited...code
so we worked with a dot net team to bring back the most common dot...api...file system, for example,
is one that people really wanted...didn't like two-ninety asynchronous...code they did more rewrite
digesting apps...existing dot net system that io...right you can do that now
...did a good partnership with dot net on that for the wintry to sort of things there
was a there's basically to buckets of feedback of the came into
the winters are things we?
Would hear from partners lot-of game developers, for example, and,
some enterprise customers about what...they really wanted
...create thread before comps the notion of virtual
...semantic...memory that is...some that is now back you graduates judge
...store right now which is pretty good there is winsoft is back there's a bunch of other
function...come back from people that told us we want to come to windows but you what
does we've unlocked those people now we also had a lot of things in windows eight and
I one where again because the duplication thing we kind of said well if there's...a unicode
...api what only the ansi one...that affected a lot of
customers and...the ansi api where make sense let's bring back the
non eecs versions of api that makes sense and really as...said it was already like on the
...not wasting disk space and it doesn't have security...never?
An issue without business model for the stored cetera villages things like...
Really amazing...great thanks for ask your questions keep on asking
...are there any api some windows universal platform for integration of
...sixty-five microsoft?
Hartman I would imagine the role rest based in as a bunch of talk share this week
...I don't know of any specifically so
...heinz rang wants to know universal
laps only in csharp and vb dot net what about cplus-plus.
Cplus-plus fully supported for universe lapped
...javascript to exact like just like the old model right sure so I also
will...wandering around earlier...big fan of moderncp
alright so...wants to know which mapping api is a new universal mapping standardize ing on
we'll support everything bing maps api supported well there was a tool about mapping
your build as well that's interesting because it...and this service
...underpinning on phone we had the nokia imap
...or windows had being I actually don't know where they've kind of mingled
had worked out but there is a common api that's universal exactly
whose engine it is I actually don't know well how much universal apps
we already so cplus-plus is fully supported on windows platform...great yes,
you have to use eecs...don't you don't use when
...url it's a lot harder?
Like I said you convert plus eecs all
...or modern are highly recommend model yeses ship that yet and,
I only mention that because I had to do that recently and I would have preferred
...get this done standard cplus-plus ...a new api ad you profiles the portable
...libraries.
Do not know that as internet questions are no problem so these guys are the
universe windows api program managers designers mccall
...sure were involved in
...I did make some decisions...at?
The let's see out someone go about building tools for creation of universal apps
ie game images.
Well, that...would be relatively easy I think you can
pick your language manage code cplus-plus.
You write to the universal api
set and now you have a library that any universal api
...can't it's just like you would
...a long as...library only uses api is common
to all platforms and right now we've got this universal
api set which is common to all platform you write a library
that now your app can be used by are your library can be used by
...the and universe lap it's a lot easier now acts totally you mentioned...
the know how shall I say the resuscitation of virtual all
...yes so you can write jets and maybe even a garbage collector
tonight so you don't want to mention...you talk about games another thing...out windows...and I
don't want to fund was thread affinity hartman affinity used a lot by
games there is in windows ten they'll be a way not to do exactly the same
...affinity because it's very hard for us to do that on a device like a phone...as a
...but they will be a way to do the notion of this workload goes here this
...negotiator wanna-be...share casual that kind of stuff and on devices where we can
...that like a pc with fan.
Will on that on a device like a phone or tablet that doesn't have a fan...yeah,
we might move workloads around a little bit about the affinity is another big one that came back to
...getting sockets virtual
alec threads did amazing thank you...
So, is there a way for you...an external
...like for...launcher or like through a manage broker?
...can't...excuse directly that you can use the launch your
...english file extensions...can launch registered schemes what
...to backhoe on...you can't say create process social exec sure because you might running a
...of support...you get the effect of that even though the actual mechanics
or slightly different so uw pita size matter...build media
...and select while developing so I want to have underwrite...windows platform out I'm going to
run on a pin number inverting like that
so your code size becomes an issue for me binary...
So, yes, so, we still have to be an engineer with wb sure you're not going to be able to run on
the one gigabyte device of your app takes ten...
Physics still apply we worked on that but we were not
successful we do have resource...so even windows through eight-point one
...this where you could have,
for example, your core code which goes everywhere and then you can have let's say
...again have some assets you have some levers asset you have some highrise assets.
And, we pulled the...the right one depending on the device in your own so you want...your
...with a tiny screen and,... or the bandwidth level of an...about the bambi
of high-rate small low-risk screen you...bring down the assets for like a four-k tv
...on that axle...that's one of...benefits of a smart sort of
...right one source
...bit bender will silo to get easier more liberal for windows
...universal windows...restrictions and silencing is allowed currently is a huge reason
...projects not even consider you a...so there...a talk here buckley
...giving a talk I think it's on this day...deployment arm...
begin because I don't know what we can say...that cut-rate answer but we feel the pain
I personally hate that...the...of every few months and says...expired yes I hate that
would passion yet so that feedback is noted yes souniversal apps for
...sharp I mean why not it's...know anything specific but.
And, I should even say this...
...know anything...so if you don't
know I'll see why not but I guess I can understand why not all right so how about wpf.
Is the gap between wpf your laps or not really...as a
desktop technology only we're going to wrap it up thank you guys were coming...sort of we're
able...mainly about the api design experience you guys...come back to channel nine
again...deeper into the whole process and thank you for your wonderful questions?